<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>XS Tech Thoughts</title>
    <link href="https://korgano.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://korgano.github.io" />
    <updated>2023-09-14T15:16:54-04:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Xavier Santana</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://korgano.github.io</id>

    <entry>
        <title>User Experience Report: Publii, Day 1</title>
        <author>
            <name>Xavier Santana</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://korgano.github.io/user-experience-report-publii-day-1/"/>
        <id>https://korgano.github.io/user-experience-report-publii-day-1/</id>
        <media:content url="https://korgano.github.io/media/posts/4/vadim-sherbakov-RcdV8rnXSeE-unsplash.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="UX"/>
            <category term="Tech"/>
            <category term="Quick Thoughts"/>

        <updated>2023-09-14T15:16:54-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://korgano.github.io/media/posts/4/vadim-sherbakov-RcdV8rnXSeE-unsplash.jpg" alt="Two flat screen monitor turned on near organizer rack inside the room." />
                    This is going to be a fairly brief, by my standards, post. Rebuilding a portfolio site from scratch is a&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://korgano.github.io/media/posts/4/vadim-sherbakov-RcdV8rnXSeE-unsplash.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Two flat screen monitor turned on near organizer rack inside the room." /></p>
                <p>This is going to be a fairly brief, by my standards, post.</p>
<p>Rebuilding a portfolio site from scratch is a time-consuming task. While I considered building one from scratch with plain old HTML, CSS, and Bootstrap, I realized that wasn't practical. So I looked for a Content Management System that was free and could upload to Github pages.</p>
<p>And I found Publii, which is all those things, and locally hosted!</p>
<p>In terms of User Interface and Experience, I much prefer it to WordPress. That's simply because Publii isn't at the stage where it has tons and tons of settings and add-ons to configure. It's got the essentials, some nice to have features, good layout, and good documentation.</p>
<p>It's good enough, and I'm fine with that.</p>
<p>There are some oddities when working with themes though. I'm currently using the free version of the <a href="https://marketplace.getpublii.com/themes/persona/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Persona theme</a>, and some of the color options don't do what you expect.</p>
<p>For one thing, I set the link hover option to a shade of green, and the text to a shade of blue. But on the nav menu and author names, the colors are reversed. (I think it looks good, so I'm not complaining, but it is weird.)</p>
<p>The animated line's color was controlled by a "Color" setting - that's right, no real details, just the word "Color". Luckily, I didn't do anything horrible in changing it, but the lack of clarity was a definite knock on the theme. The inability to further customize the animation is annoying, but perhaps that an exclusive feature of the paid themes.</p>
<p>Speed and performance of the software is good, and I <strong>greatly </strong>appreciate the ability to choose "Save draft" as an option before I save anything I post.</p>
<p>One limitation of the software is that it seems excessively blog focused. You can't actually make a standard page. You just make posts, and then use a specialized page to show off all the posts with a specific tag. It's quite odd, but not a huge negative.</p>
<p>One <strong>huge </strong>positive is the fact that I can actually set the width of various elements quickly and easily. So no huge amounts of wasted space on my site!</p>
<p>In terms of content, it's a mixed bag. Even though I have backups of most of my previous content from my old UXZone.io site, it's not in an easily importable format. So It'll be a slow process of getting the old content extracted from the backup and converted to the new site.</p>
<p>But hey, at least I didn't lose it all!</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
